Finding aid to the John Morton Greene papers CA.MS.00080
Smith College Archives
John Morton Greene papers
1833-1997
Smith College Archives
Greene, John Morton, 1830-1919.
CA.MS.00080
3.5 linear feet (8 containers)
Pastor of Sophia Smith, generally regarded as the originator of the idea of founding Smith College as a college for women. Papers contain biographical information, personal and professional correspondence, recollections, journals, manuscripts, photographs, and published works. There are also articles and clippings pertaining to his life, Sophia Smith, and the early history and founding of Smith College.
Biographical / Historical
John Morton Greene, Sophia Smith's pastor, is generally regarded as the originator of the idea of founding Smith College as a college for women. Born in Hadley, Mass. on March 12, 1830, he was an 1853 graduate of Amherst College, which also granted him the A.M. in 1856 and D.D. in 1881. In 1857 he married Louisa Dickinson of North Amherst, an 1857 graduate of Mount Holyoke Seminary. In the same year, he was installed as the pastor at the Congregational church at Hatfield, where he remained for eleven years. In Hatfield he met Sophia Smith. In 1868 he was called to the pastorate at the Congregational Church at South Hadley, Mass. Two years later he went to the Eliot Congregational Church in Lowell, Mass., where he remained for thirty years. After retiring from regular pastoral duties in 1910, Greene assisted in the establishment of a mission in Maine. He died April 28, 1919.
John Morton Greene was a trustee of Smith College almost continuously from its founding in 1871 until his death. In addition, he served on the board of trustees of Mount Holyoke Seminary (now Mount Holyoke College), 1866-1875; and was president of the board of trustees at the French Protestant College in Springfield, 1885-1889. As advisor to Sophia Smith, he was also instrumental in the founding of Smith Academy in Hatfield, and acted in a similar capacity for Miss Rogers to found the Rogers Hall School in Lowell, where he acted as president of its board of trustees, 1892-1909. For over forty years he was one of the overseers of the charity fund at Amherst College.
Scope and Contents
The John Morton Greene Papers contain materials including biographical information, personal and professional correspondence, journals, manuscripts, photographs, and published works. There are also articles and clippings pertaining to his life, Sophia Smith, and the early history and founding of Smith College.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical
II. Correspondence
III. Journals
IV. Publications
V. Scrapbooks
Additional Formats
The following information is also available online as part of the Five College Archives Digital Access Project
1. General Correspondence, 1856-1917
2. Personal Journal (entries written 1861-1876 only)
3. "My Notes On Smith College," ca. 1910-1917 (A 129-page booklet of handwritten notes by John Morton Greene recording his recollections of the circumstances surrounding the founding of Smith College.)
4. Scrapbook, 1860-1918 (A 100-page scrapbook consisting predominantly of newspaper clippings related to women's education and academic affairs at Smith College, with particular reference to Greene's role in the College's founding; also, some published articles related to women's education at other U.S. institutions.)
5. Published Writings, 1875-1916 (Writings by JMG published in periodicals: Includes his "Early History of Smith College" [a 12-part series appearing in the Daily Hampshire Gazette, 1891-93], also correspondence related to it; a "Sketch of the Life and Character of Miss Sophia Smith"; "An Inside View of Smith College," published in a Lowell, Mass. newspaper in 1882; and other occasional pieces.)
6. Louisa Dickinson Greene Papers, 1854-1881 (6 letters and 2 other writings by the wife of John Morton Greene.)
7. Obituaries and Retrospectives on John Morton Greene, 1919-1930
Related Material
See also: 10.Founding of the College 10.Sophia Smith Papers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were donated over a period of time by John Morton Greene and his daughter, Helen French Greene.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Congregational churches--Clergy.; Clergy--Massachusetts.; Greene, John Morton, 1830-1919.; Greene, Louisa Dickinson, 1830-1881.; Smith College--Administration.; Greene, Helen French, 1868-; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Hubbard, George W. (George Warner); Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.; Smith, Sophia, 1796-1870.; Wells, Daniel White, 1842-
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  - Addresses: Centennial of the Birth of Sophia Smith, 1853; 1896 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Biography and Genealogy, 1864-1997 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Household Servants, 1863 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, correspondence re: death of, 1919; 1930 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Rogers Hall School, 1901-1919 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - General: Watch- see artifacts, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Greene, Louisa, 1904 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1860; 1879; undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: Portraits, 1913; undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Portrait: Clippings and Correspondence, 1894-1938 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Photograph: Emily Dickinson, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Professional Employment: Appleton St. Church, Lowell, MA, 1870; 1879 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Professional Employment: Eliot Church, Lowell, MA, 1881-1948; undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Professional Employment: Eliot Church, Lowell, MA: Sermons, 1887-1909 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Professional Employment: Enfield, CT Church, 1866 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Professional Employment: Hatfield: Congregational Church, Hatfield MA, 1857-1925 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Professional Employment: South Hadley: First Church, South Hadley, MA, 1870 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Smith Charities, 1875 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Sophia Smith: Excerpts from journals, 1860-1911 (Box 17, Folder 19)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Index (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - from: Burton, Marion LeRoy, 1909-1918 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - to Alcott, Mr., 1881; 1883 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - from: Ames, Henrietta, 1916 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - to: Brown, Nina Eliza, '82, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - to: Caverno, Julia Harwood, '87, 1916 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - to: Clark, Elizabeth (Lawrence), '83, 1911 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - to: Clark, Josephine Adelaide, '80, 1910; 1914 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - to: Cone, Kate (Morris), '79, 1910 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - to: Dickinson, Mrs. (mother-in-law), 1886 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - to: Fuller, Grace P., 1910 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - to: Greene, Helen F., '91, 1898-1905 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - from: Greene, Louisa Dickinson.(before marriage), 1856-57 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - from: Greene, Louisa Dickinson to others, 1854-81 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - from: Greene, Louisa Dickinson to JMG, 1866-75 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - to: Greene, Louisa Dickinson (wife), 1863; 1864; 1878; 1880 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - to: Greene, Louisa (daughter), 1864; 1895; 1899; 1902 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - from: Greene, Lulu (Louisa) (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - to: Greene, William (brother), 1853 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - from: Greene, William S., 1872 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - to: Hill, Edith Naomi, '03, 1911; 1916 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - to: Hubbard, George W., 1868-1879 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - to: Jackson, Alice, '98, 1904 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - to: Jordan, Mary Augusta, 1911 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - to: Keyes, Bertha A., 1917 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - to: Mardus, Mrs., 1916 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - from: Mason, John W., 1894 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - from: Northrop, B.G., 1888 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - from: Noyes, Lucia (Clapp), '81, 1917 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - to: Park, Edward A., 1979 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - to: Parker, Mrs. Henry, 1906 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - from: Scott, Mary Augusta, 1911 (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - from: Seelye, L. Clark, 1881-1918 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - to: Smith, Sophia, 1869-70 (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - to Tucker, Charlotte (Cheever), 1891-92 (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - to Tyler, William S., 1873; 1882-84 (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - from: Tyler, William S., 1875 (Box 18, Folder 37)
  - from: Warner, Elisa A., 1882 (Box 18, Folder 38)
  - from: Wells, D. W., 1893-1916 (Box 18, Folder 39)
  - to: Whipple, Mrs. Shipman, 1910 (Box 18, Folder 40)
- Series III. Journals
  - Journals, 1883-1919 (Box 18.1, Box 18.2)
  - Journal and scrapbook index, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Journal excerpts, 1861-1917 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Journals, 1833-1919 (Box 20)
- Series IV. Publications
  - Sketch of the Life and Character of Sophia Smith, 1875 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Early History of Smith College, Daily Hampshire Gazette, 1891-93 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Early History of Smith College, Correspondence, 1881-1919 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Early History of Smith College, Typescript, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Happy Wedlock, 1900 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Little Things for Little Folk, parts I-IV, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Little Things for Little Folk, parts V-VII, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Looking on the Bright Side, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Friendship, 1865 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Semi-Centennial of the Eliot Church, Lowell, MA, 1881 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Publications: General, 1897 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Inside View of Smith College, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Pub. Miscellaneous, 1909 (Box 21, Folder 13)
- Series V. Scrapbook
  - Index (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - pages 1-10, 1872 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - pages 11-20, 1872-73 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - pages 21-30, 1875-77 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - pages 31-40, 1888 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - pages 41-50, 1873-82 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - pages 51-60, 1894-96 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - pages 61-70, 1893-1913 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - pages 71-80, 1896-1907 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - pages 81-90, 1906-1916 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - pages 91- end, 1866-79 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Books pertaining to Smith College- addresses by Seelye, Tyler, etc.
    - Greene, John Morton: "My Notes on Smith College", 1883 (Box 22, Folder 12)